Hello everyone welcome
back to another session.
Today we are going to
look into the genetics
of cardiopulmonary
disorders. I'm
Vishwa Rajagopalan
again and welcome back.
So the learning objectives
of this session are
to differentiate
clinical presentations of
classical congenital heart
defects and syndromes
their etiology diagnostics
and recurrent risks
and therapeutic aspects as
well as much as possible
and to differentiate clinical
presentations of classical
cardiogenetic syndromes
and identify their causes
their you know diagnostics
and recurrent risks and
then to recognize cardinal
features and genetic bases
and inheritance etc for
pulmonary genetic conditions
and then to assess the risks
and determine appropriate
genetic tests to identify
and or to confirm the
diagnosis. So we look into
what kind of tests are
relevant for given conditions.
We'll focus on broader
congenital heart effects.
We will focus on the known
genetic causes in the
cardiovascular area and also
in the pulmonary area, some
representative examples
okay so this these slides
complex one blueprint um
this indicates the importance
and relevance of what you
are studying where do you
need to focus how is it
important for your board
exam in less than a year um
and this is usmle's uh you
know step on blueprint um
And these are, you know,
guide, and they can't list
everything, but these are
representative, you know, to,
you know, pieces of information
to give you some idea.
so um so this is to give
you a note that uh um so
please review some relevant
genetics lecture materials
that you have learned
in the second year and
particularly in the first
year for better understanding
it's not uh feasible
to re uh you know learn
or re-teach all these things
in the defined time um
so we will go over a few
concepts here and there
to recall our memory but
please do refresh your
memory based on the previous
concepts uh that if you
don't understand or if
you could prepare ahead um
I've also provided some
case study questions and
answers towards the end but
we'll see a few examples
uh in between in during
the lecture session Okay,
so congenital heart
defects, they occur in
about 0.5% of live births,
and the most common
condition is ventricular
septum defect,
VSD,
which is an opening
between the two ventricles
in the ventricular
and intraventricular
septum, and it can be
at different levels,
at a mid-level or basal
level or apical level.
Now, differential diagnosis
for congenital heart
defects could be multifactorial
in 70% of the cases.
And empiric congenital
heart disease carries
a recurrence risk of
3 to 5%. So what's a
recurrence risk? It's a
likelihood that a hereditary
trait or disorder
present in one family
member will occur again
in other family members.
Okay.
So, and the risk can be reduced
by maternal folate intake.
So,
and the, so again, it's
a statistic, recurrence
risk is a statistic that
estimates the probability
that a condition present
in one or more family
members will reoccur in
another member in the
same or future generations.
So that's recurrence
risk. And again, maternal
folate intake can help.
So majority we saw
multifactorial. In a minority
set of cases, environmental
or teratogenic,
maternal consumption
of ethanol, alcohol,
diabetes,
and phenylketonuria,
fever in the first semester, AC
inhibitors,
anticonversants, et cetera.
SSRIs can lead to primary
pulmonary hypertension.
Lithium ingestion
could contribute to
Epstein's anomaly. So,
these are some of the
associations that have
been formed so far.
And in genetic cases are known
in about 25% of the cases.
So, chromosomal anomalies,
the gene mengerine
disorders. That doesn't mean
that in the remaining 70
% or so, there are no genetic
conditions. It's just
based on the information
that is available. So,
more and more research will
be helpful to understand
all the idiopathic or,
you know, unknown causes.
So, frequency of general
heart defects. So,
as I said before, BSD
is the most common,
30-45% and followed
by pulmonary stenosis,
atrial septal defect,
pulmonary stenosis, I don't
know if you have gone
through this before. so it's
an obstruction in the
between in the pulmonary
valve at or below or in
that area and then atrial
septal defect it's the
persisting opening of all this
persisting opening in
the intra atrial septum
patent and persistent ductal
arteriosus you know between
the aorta and pulmonary
artery there should be
an opening that should close
soon after birth shortly
after birth but it
continues so pda so that all
these things leads to
mixing right all this to
shunting of blood in uh in
a in an incorrect direction
mixing of oxygenated
deoxygenated bread etc um
pulmonary stenosis case of
um you know right ventricular
hypertrophy and so on
aortic valve stenosis um as
it says the obstruction of
the aortic valve that leads
to improper inability to
properly push the blood out
into the aorta from the
left ventricle. Co-actration
of the aorta you will see
it's an obstruction at the
arterial level in the arm
and the one of the branches.
Transposition of great
arteries it's the great
arteries being mixed
up left versus aorta
versus pulmonary artery
positioned incorrectly.
It's very risky especially
the dextrotransposition.
um because of uh you
know significant mixing
tetralogy of fallow four
conditions you will learn uh
or you would have learned
um and then hypoplastic
left heart syndrome so
the the the percentage the
frequency um you know
keeps reducing based on uh
you know studies um
congenital heart defects with
most likely syndromic
genetic causes okay most
likely syndromic have been
found to be tetralogy of
fellow, supravalvular
aortic stenosis, coactation,
AV canal defect, and
pulmonary stenosis.
So first of all, a syndrome,
a syndrome is a group
of, group of traits or
conditions that tend to occur
together and characterize
a recognizable disease.
So some syndromes are known
to have genetic causes,
right, and many of these are
pathognomonic associations
with specific syndromes
these conditions that
are listed and let's
take a closer look at uh
you know uh some of these
trisomies right trisomies
um so again I want to
tell you something so it's
you need to know um you know
about different syndromes
their clinical presentation
etc and it's not feasible
to go through everything
so I've highlighted few
things in bold um so please
focus on those definitely but
also you need to learn
other things as well but
definitely the ones in the
board are very important for
you to keep in memory uh so
that you recognize an exam
item as early as possible as
quickly as possible um and
also you know for your
boards and your clinical
practice etc so trisomy there
are three major types of
trisomies 21 trisomy is the
popular Down syndrome. There
is mild intellectual
disability there compared to 18
trisomy or 13 trisomy which
those patients have severe
intellectual disability.
So Down syndrome, milder,
and it happens in 50%. The
recurrence risk for trisomies
in general is usually low
with exception of parents
who are Robertsonian
translocation as in T13 or T21.
So sorry that I'm jumping
here, but the recurrence
risk for T13, T20, generally
they are usually low.
Exceptions are those
parents who are
Robertsonian translocation
as in. So what's
Robertsonian? I mean,
we will see that.
I think we have seen
already in the previous last
year. So please refresh
your memory from that.
Let's focus on the
clinical aspects here more.
So
T18 and T31, again, severe
intellectual disability
in congenital heart
disease greater than 90
percentage congenital
heart disease again greater
than 80 percentage um and
then um the most common
heart defect in downs is av
canal it um atrio ventricular
canal type defect
including bst and ast in um
edward syndrome the congenital
heart defect it could
be a variety of type again
in syndrome it could be a
variety of types the key
point is empiric trisomy
the recurrence risk is one
percent this you need to
remember it is a low recurrence
risk but it increases
to doubles in older moms okay
so and it can be detected
by karyotyping if you
see last year we saw the
different methodologies
applications of molecular genetics
various different techniques
we saw chromosome,
karyotyping, G-banding,
you know, a variety of
things, you know, FISH,
which is fluorescence into
the hybridization, and
then microarrays, arrays
comparative genomic
hybridization, we saw sequencing,
right, PCR, cloning,
Sanger sequencing, or next
-generation sequencing,
and then some of the gene
modification technologies.
so those are you know
all relevant here for
diagnostic purposes treatment
as well which are emerging
but we are focusing on
you know these conditions
so please just refreshing
those in your memory
Turner syndrome right Turner
syndrome these patients
have 45x and these again
can be detected with
regular karyotyping. They
are short stature. So,
shocks is the gene that
is significantly involved.
These patients are
growth hormone resistant,
but they do respond to
high dose growth hormone.
And primarily, they
have amenorrhea
or infertility. And there is a
let's see normal intelligence
thankfully and the
congenital heart defects 35
percent especially coactation
of ayurta so on the left
slide you can see coactation
of ayurta have a differential
blood pressure high
blood pressure before the
point of coactation which is
an obstruction at the
arterial level branch arterial
level and then low blood
pressure beyond the point of
coactation so that's a
clinically useful parameter
when you suspect a patient
with turner syndrome some
of the clinical features
you see dysmorphic features
like lymphedema webbed neck
shield chest then you can
see that then immediately
what you need to do in the
outpatient setting you want
to quickly do a check blood
pressure not just on the
arm but also on the hind
limb um so that can um uh
that can help um so um so that
so that can help the patient
in the diagnosis and then
every empiric turner
recurrence risk is not elevated
um okay so we can move on
um and also I want to make
one more point here that
the again recurrence risk
is negligible most of this
arise from non-disjunction
events which means
failure of the chromosomes
to separate okay that occur
post meiotically and most
renal syndrome females
start out at 46 xx or 46 xy
and they lose one sex
chromosome due to meiotic
non-disjunction as I mentioned
and it's important to
take a look at a large
number of cells if they have
any y chromosome If they
do, they need to remove it
or else you can see the
gonadoblastoma is a risk.
Microdeletion
syndromes, they can
be detected using
fish or array.
Again, you're now
getting into smaller
resolution, finer
resolution in banding.
So you need better
techniques such as fish than
karyotyping or G-banding.
Desjard syndrome 22q 11.2 there
the congenital heart disease
risk the the higher chance
is to draw the fellow which
is the number one cause
also interrupted aortic
arch or ventricular septal
defect abnormal phases thymic
so one of the so these are
some of the common conditions
like cleft lip palate
and then thymic abnormalities
hypocalcemia one of the
easy way to remember mnemonic
is catch-22 of course
it's we don't discuss this
with you know families but
it's helped it helps for
you to remember catch-22 is
c-a-t-c-h as you can see
chd abnormal faces thymic
clefting and hypocalcemia
um william syndrome uh is uh
due to elastin uh abnormality
dysmorphic elfin like
features cocktail party
personality where people are very
social but the content of
their conversation may not
be I may not have a
significant amount of substance
so that's the lack of stranger
anxiety delusion of gene
involved in amygdala or
fear response so they are
quite social and then oops sorry
and then yeah hypercalcemia
milder intellectual
disability and most of the
time it's a supravalvular
aortic stenosis due to mutation
in the micro deletion of
the elastin gene and the
recurrence risk is again
low less than one percent
but if 50 percentage if parent
is affected okay and it's
autosomal dominant and you
can again fish and array
techniques are useful to
detect it I've given some
pictures towards the right
for you to understand their
clinical appearance and
presentation okay single gene
syndromes single gene
syndromes are um for example uh
new names and charge
syndromes they are detected by
sequencing so the final uh the
gene level you go sequencing
will be helpful than some
of the low resolution
you know g-banding so
autosomal dominant um
ras pathway mutations
are involved um so these
are of the genes
especially ptp and 11 is
involved so please remember
some of the key genes
as you study dysmorphic
features of the face
and chest neck etc eyes
and then ears and then
mind intellectual
disability 25 percent uh no
infertility coagulopathy
can be seen and then
what's the cardiac
condition? Pulmonary valvular
stenosis, dysplasia is
the number one cause.
Also, hypertrophic
cardiomyopathy. Recurrence
risk is 50%, okay,
for affected probands.
Now, Cthard syndrome includes
C-H-A-R-G-E, coloboma,
heart defects in 85%, with
a variety of types, atresia,
retarded growth and
development, genital
defects, and ear
abnormalities and deafness.
autosomal dominant chd7
this is the key gene so just
remember chd7 for child
syndrome recurrence risk is
again 50 in effect if an
affected parent reproduces
otherwise it's just
less than one to
five percent um for
this condition so um
and and you can detect with
the gene panel if you look
at new nines right a bunch
of genes are there So,
there are commercially gene
panels should be available
where if you suspect patients
based on this clinical
condition, the genetic counselor
can, you know, recommend,
clinician can recommend
these genetic tests so
they can nail it down to
which gene so that noon and
syndrome could be confirmed.
and as more and more studies
evolve hopefully there
could be some gene therapies
in the future there are
some conditions gene therapy
is emerging for many
conditions in cancer and other
conditions as well so
you know sickle cell
anemia is a great
example right CRISPR has
become it has been
approved so it's a you know
hopeful future okay
recap quickly what have
we seen so far, what
conditions are associated
with what syndromes
mainly. Tetralogy are
followed significantly
with Deschamps syndrome.
Williams syndrome,
supravalvular aortic stenosis.
Turner syndrome,
coactation of aorta,
Downs, atrioventricular
canal defect,
and Noonan syndrome, pulmonary
stenosis or dysplasia.
So these are some examples
for you to remember
the most common conditions
okay case study one again
this is not perfectly in a
board style but helps you to
remember some of the key
points you have seen so far
the woman is presenting
for prenatal care at eight
peaks of gestational age what's
the empiric risk of fetus
her fetus has for a
congenital heart defect any
congenital heart defect right
so typically it's 0.5 percent
point excuse me 0.8 percent
of all live births the
empiric risk of is 0.8 and
the risk is increased so the
second question is a level
2 fetal ultrasound at 20
weeks suggests a congenital
heart disease defect and
fetal echocardiography reveals
a vst there is no other
family member family history
of chd and this couple wants
to have more children if
no cause is found what is
the chance that their next
child will also have a chd
and what's the answer the
recurrence risk is increased
due to previously
affected child of unknown
cause so three to five
percent is the recurrence
risk and how can you
reduce it um you can reduce
it by um mother consuming
folic acid okay and
what is the recurrence
risk if a chromosomal
karyotype on amniocentesis
reveals the affected
fetus has trisomy 21 the
answer is one percent
overall or two two times
if the maternal age
if there is a maternal
age associated risk and
what is the recurrence risk
if a chromosomal microarray
instead revealed the
fetus had a chromosome
22 q 11.2 micro deletion
so the answer is the
recurrence risk is negligible
but they should check
to make sure if they are
not mildly symptomatic
carriers because if they
do, there is a 50% chance
of recurrence in future
pregnancies. You can see
the questions go little
into the details. So you
need to focus on some
aspects and memorizing them.
So Morphin syndrome is
another important condition.
Patients can have abnormal
long legs and arms versus
the trunk ratio, which is
called dolicosteinomelia.
Elongated fingers,
elongated toes, arachnodactyly,
positive wrist sign.
Let's see.
Yeah, positive wrist sign.
And then thumb signs,
sternal deformities.
So, it's essentially
a fibrillin
1 disorder in many cases.
Fibrillin 1 is an
extracellular matrix elastin
-associated glycoprotein
and with a TGF binding
protein. Now, 50% it's
de novo, 50% inherited.
Clinical morphine syndrome
is very important as it
is associated with
aortic root dilatation or
aortic root dissection with
ectopia lentis. Now, in
many cases, you can see
FBN1 mutation. If you see,
then it is more of a
definitive morphine syndrome.
The problem, Bigger
problem is it could be
deleterious, life-threatening,
aortic root dilatation
dissection, plus a combination
of systemic findings
greater than 7 points
means morpheon syndrome.
I have given in the, if
you see on the bottom
left or bottom right, you
can see I mentioned the
supplemental notes for
more information. Whenever
you see that, please go
back to the file that
I enclosed, where you can
see even more information,
for example, diagnostic
criteria and so on.
There is a point system
for this called Ghent
criteria, and that
helps to determine the
likelihood of the presence
of Morphin syndrome.
Okay, so that's the
important thing here.
Let's see the risk
of aortic root
dilatation. If it is untreated,
mean life expectancy
can be just 40 years.
Okay, but with treatment,
patients can live up to
even 70 years, which means
it's important to timely
detect because aortic
root irritation or aortic
dissection can be just suddenly
people can die okay people
can think that it's heart
attack but it is aortic
you know problem so
periodically echocardiography
6 to 12 months every
64 months intermittent
ct mr etc based on
the diameter of aorta
greater than four and
a half centimeter.
And if it keeps
increasing, it's a, you
know, one needs to
very closely monitor
via at least echo.
And then beta blockade
can help decrease the
aortic wall stress.
Losartan is a
aortic, excuse me,
angiotensin receptor
blocker that can help
prophylactic aortic
root replacement if the
patient is ready for it.
And precautions, you know,
you know, contact sports
reduction, et cetera. All
those things can help save
the patient and live longer.
Morphine-like syndrome.
So, so far we some
Morphine syndrome, some
syndromes which mimic
Morphine syndrome, but not
quite. So, they are LDS,
Lois-Diet syndrome, which
have morphonoid plus
abnormal morphonoid,
morphine-like features,
Bifid, Avila, abnormal
palate. Their autosomal
dominant mutations include
TGF beta receptor 1 and 2.
Homocystinuria, there you
can see cbs gene involved
okay cbs gene mental
deterioration high homocysteine
and then beale syndrome
has a cca um and then
fbn2 mutation particularly
so remember the here we saw
fbn1 that's morphan and
here proper here it is
fbn2 that's beale's and then
men um again it has a RET
gene and then SGS-SKI gene.
So the point is, consider
if morphonoid habitus
plus atypical symptoms or
no FBN1 mutation for
morphonoid-like syndromes.
Before that, I want to say
one interesting piece of
information. For aortic
dissection, there are some
celebrities that have had
they have died um because
of this suddenly right
like john ritter alan thick
doug lamalfa and lindsey
graham recently so
it's important to keep
a close track of these
conditions in patients moment
you see clinical conditions
you know that represents
morphine or morphine okay
case two a 15 year old
female is noted to be taller
than predicted for her
family. She's thin with
disproportionately long
limbs and fingers, has
depression of the
sternum, given a sunken in
appearance to her chest,
scoliosis, and skin stray.
Without further
information, which of the
following should be in your
differential diagnosis?
So, and you also want
to think, so the direct
answer is all of the
above. So, for learning
purposes, let's ask the
question, if you see STRI,
then, like,
you can see some,
the patient has that, right?
If you see Bifid Uvula,
right, what does that
indicate? um that
indicates the lds we saw
in the previous slide
low state syndrome
if mental retaliation
then homocysteine urea and then
if you see the congenital
joint contractures then
patients can have bill
syndrome um if the fbn1
gene is testing negative
then you need to think all
these options and others
like SGS and MEN2A and
B so this is just an example
for you to understand
of course you it's less
likely for a patient to
have all these things but
the point is you need to
understand what's the key
point in each of these
so it's a good piece of
grammar of memorization.
EDS, important, right? We
know there's an EDS, you know,
center in the Old
Westville campus.
It's a heterogeneous group of
hereditary connective
tissue disorders
which share common
cardinal features
such as joint hypermobility,
skin hyperextensibility,
and fragility and
connective tissue fragility.
So, connective tissue
disorder, which includes
valvular heart disease
and other things in
uterine, bowel, wherever
connective tissues are,
it can be impaired.
Skin is lax, abnormal
scouring, bruising, etc.
Joint flexibility is a
key feature you can see.
Combined incidence is 1
to 3,100 to 1 to 5,000
largely, but not exclusively
a collagen gene mutation.
Okay. All right. So,
okay.
So,
EDS types. What are
the different types
of EDS? Hypermobile
EDS, which is the most
common type of Ehlers
-Danlos Syndrome.
It's rare, non-progressive,
and it's associated
with mitral valve
prolapse and aortic
dilatation. it is not
typically life-threatening
and the clinical diagnosis
of this condition
is simultaneous presence
of all these three criteria
there are a lot more
details involved in the
diagnosis but just to give
you a taste of it criterion
one is about the generalized
joint hypermobility
criterion two it's about
two or more types of
the features a b c must
be present and three, all
of the following prerequisites
must be met. So what
are those following? I
believe I would have given
that information in
supplemental notes for your
just information.
In the details of
supplemental notes, I don't
expect you to memorize
that for the exam purposes.
But the classic EDS,
the greatest degree of skin
laxity. okay this and then
more commonly as we saw
about its mitral valve
prolapse and it is not life
-threatening thankfully now
when it comes to hypermobility
scales there are some
scales the bayton scale
which is a nine point scale
the higher the number the
higher the laxity of the joints
and the positive results
test mean the patient
likely has some joint
hypermobility syndrome. And then
we saw the generalized joint
hypermobility criterion
one, right? So that's the
minimum score, the cutoff.
So it's greater than six
if prepubertal greater than
five for puberty, up to
age 50, and so on. So
different criteria are, you
know, used to measure this.
So hyperextension is
best measured using a
methodology called goniometry
to quantify the exact
degree of hyperextension.
And the minimum
score can vary by age,
as we see in this slide.
okay um so the uh the bs
right the weight and scale
one point is given at each
of the nine spots if a person
exceeds the normal range
of motion um thumbs elbows
knees and so on so different
ways are used to measure
how much hyper um so the
degree of hypermobility
is hyperextension is assessed
cardinal skin
manifestations include
skin hyperextensibility as
you can see in the figure
at neutral sites greater
than one and half centimeter
at other sites greater
than three centimeters skin
fragility it's easy to get
bruised and wound healing
can be delayed dystropic
scarring atropic and so
on often spontaneous at
pressure points like elbows
knees and chin okay what
are the different types of
in continuing on the different
types of eds vascular
let's focus on a little
bit on the vascular type.
The prevalence is 1 in 50, 200
,000. An autosomal dominant.
Etiology is significantly
called 3A1 mutation.
And then the common features
are mild joint hypermobility.
Predominantly
peripheral joints.
And then easy bruising.
Prematurely aged appearance.
And then loss of
subcutaneous fat,
characteristic
****** appearance,
thin skin with prominent
vasculature, early
varicose veins,
rupture of hollow organs
such as bowel, uterine,
arterial vessels,
particularly coronary
aorta, and so on.
Outcomes, median age at
death is about 51 years,
typically due to vascular
dissection or rupture.
5.3% mortality in
pregnancy primarily due to
vascular occasionally
uterine rupture. Management,
bring the patient to
maintain normal tension
and regular vascular
ultrasound, CT, etc.
Avoid contact sports, isometric
exertion, elective surgery,
and wear mid-alert
bracelet. Have
emergency plans,
emergent evacuation,
evaluation, excuse
me, for unusual pain.
Okay, so, again,
call 3A1 is something
you need to remember.
Rarely call 1A1.
If you see that
mutation, most likely
it's vascular EDS,
or vice versa.
Okay, case study. So here,
this patient has a 26
-year-old female with
joint hypermobility,
recurrent subluxations,
chronic arthralgias, recent
spontaneous rectus abdominis,
muscle tear, physical
exam reveals peripheral
joint hypermobility,
mild increased skin
dist extensibility,
increased vascular
prominence over chest,
dorsum of hands and feet
and paucity of subcutaneous
****** subcutaneous fat with
prematurely aged appearance.
Mother died in her 40s of
ruptured brain aneurysm,
similar ****** appearance.
Most likely diagnosis,
vascular EDS, we
just saw. Again,
the diagnostic test is, we just
saw, called 3A1 mutation. Okay,
familial
hypercholesterolemia. So FH
presentation is markedly
elevated LDL and
cholesterol levels.
Look at the numbers.
Enormously high.
Homozygotes particularly
have 50% mortality by 30
years of age from atherosclerosis.
Could be myocardial
infarction which is heart
attack, cerebrovascular
abnormalities, or
peripheral vascular disease.
Heterozygotes have 50%
mortality by 60 years of age,
okay.
Longer life, but still
they're also at risk.
Significant cholesterol,
you know, increase.
Etiology, primarily
LDL receptor, low
-density lipoprotein
receptor gene
mutation, mostly
autosomal dominant.
The lower the residual
LDLR function,
the more severe the familial
hypercholesterolemia
phenotype, okay. Okay,
so treatment, oh genes,
additional genes that
have been recently
identified include APOB,
PCSK9, I think it's a
typo here, sorry about
that, PCSK9, I believe.
Treatment, as you
can imagine, restrict
the dietary cholesterol
consumption,
Statins, the popular
statins, HNG-CoA reductase
inhibitors. Microsomal
transfer protein
inhibitors are available
like lometopoide and
antisense oligonucleotides
are also available.
Plasmapheresis,
cardiac or liver
transplantation in
you know if these
are not sufficient.
Interesting thing is
there are recent clinical
trials are ongoing where
at least one company
is looking into only one
-time treatment for high
cholesterol levels,
only one-time treatment
in their entire life and
that they believe, they
hope will be sufficient
to treat the patient
using CRISPR technology.
So, the monogenic
conditions are the better
chance of getting
gene therapy than you
know let's say multi
polygenic conditions.
So we'll wait for the
future studies. Hypertrophic
cardiomyopathy is one of the
genetic cardiomyopathies.
Okay so it's isolated
primary hypertrophic
cardiomyopathy, autosomal
dominant, sarcomia protein,
sarcomatic protein genes.
You need to remember that.
In syndromic
conditions, variable
inheritance modes,
NUNA and SPOMP,
Frederick's Ataxia,
Fabry, these things can
be associated with
genetic cardiomyopathies,
particularly hypertrophic.
Dilated, it's
autosomal dominant
again. The difference is
cytoskeletal protein
genes. So hypertrophic is
sarcomere, dilated is cytoskeletal
predominantly. doesn't
mean that's the only thing
there are lamin dilated
cardiomyopathy there are
other types too but remember
cytoskeletal um syndromic
um associated with
mitochondrial abnormalities
okay and then arvc arvc arvc
erythmogenic right
ventricular cardiomyopathy or
dysplasia autosomal dominant
uh intracellular adhesion
genes remember that
intracellular adhesion genes
Again, for this, I've
seen some clinical
trials ongoing for
gene therapies.
Clinical considerations,
all can be present with,
all of these can present
with sudden cardiac
death. That could be
devastating for families.
Sudden cardiac death,
arrhythmia, syncope, and or
congestive heart failure.
So, in the interest
of time, I'm moving
on. management includes
avoiding strenuous
athletic activity,
preload reduction,
assessing the risk for
sudden cardiac death,
and then treatment
with beta blockade,
ICD, automatic implantable
cardiovascular defibrillator,
surgical myomectomy,
transplantation. There are
multiple drugs that are
coming. Nice drugs are coming.
Maverickampton, if I'm right,
that's one example that
I can think of some lot of
studies are ongoing so love
duty syndrome this is more
of an electrophysiological
channel disorder electrical
conduction disorder
autosomal dominant a lot of
associated with the romano ward
syndrome in an isolated
condition uh syndromic gerwal
land nielsen uh anderson
Teville, Timothy syndrome.
Main thing is
sudden cardiac death
is a big problem
in young people,
10 to 15% of the cases with
ventricular arrhythmias,
to set us to point as
ventricular fibrillation.
So often precipitated by
exertion, high stress, QT
prolonging medication. So these
patients should not consume
QT prolonging medications.
There's a list I think
available um especially for
the next condition that I'm
that I can tell you more
um management um management
includes avoiding strenuous
activity uh and emotional
stress avoiding qt prolonging
medications instituting
better blockade consider a
defibrillator defibrillator
can be really life-saving
okay preventative okay brugada
syndrome is another such
condition but in this case
the there is a um so here
is long qt here it is
significantly uh mi like
feature in the ekg there's
st elevation there are
three different types and
you can see the additional
information I'm given here
um um so sudden cardiac
death is again big problem
here okay mostly male
are predisposed for that
uh again these conditions
particularly brigada is
not easily found during
birth it takes time for it
to uh manifest it takes
time uh in the in the 30s
in men for instance it It
becomes more, you know,
clinical presentation,
triggered by fever
and autosomal
dominant. It could be
monogenic or oligogenic
or even polygenic.
Monogenic condition,
sodium channel current,
potassium current, and
many non-coding genes
are also known to be
involved in many of
these conditions,
particularly in Brugada.
Some drugs to be avoided
are antiarrhythmic
drugs, psychotropic
drugs. And there is a nice
website, BrugadaDogs
.org, which lists all the
drugs that needs to be
avoided, that must be
avoided, that are preferably
avoided, and so on.
So these are important.
Otherwise, people
take these drugs and
then they put their life
at greater risk of
sudden cardiac death.
Okay.
So far, we have seen a whole
bunch of cardiac genetic
abnormalities. Let's
quickly dive into pulmonary
abnormalities.
representative one is cystic
fibrosis. Classical clinical
triad include chronic
sinopulmonary infection, exocrine
pancreatic insufficiency,
elevated sweat, chloride,
and sodium levels.
It's autosomal recessive.
Mutation is CFTR gene,
cystic fibrosis transmembrane
conductance regulator.
That leads to reduction in
the function and then faulty
chloride transport and
sodium reabsorption um then
the most common mutation
is remember it's delta f508
delta f508 um that leads
to misfolded cftr protein
and epidemiologically
highest carrier frequency in
caucasians okay um and the
diagnosis is by newborn
screening uh 95 percentage of
the time elevated immunoreactive
IRT. So, that's an
important newborn screening
methodology. There is
elevated IRT that suggests the
patient may have CFTR,
cystic fibrosis. And then you
can do sweat testing and
all those things for, you
know, validating with multiple
tests. So, the essential
problem is that CFTR channel
protein doesn't get to
the cell membrane to exert
its ion channel function.
Okay.
Many males are infertile
due to congenital absence
of vast difference. So
that's here. Clinical
features. Sinopulmonary
disease, chronic cough,
nasal polyposis, recurrent
pulmonary infection,
GA manifestations
include neonatal
meconium ileus,
pancreatic insufficiency,
hepatic dysfunction,
salt loss syndrome due to
chronic metabolic alkylosis.
Again, as I said, male
infertility associated with
congenital absence of
vast difference. And then
atypical cystic fibrosis
now increasingly identified
due to newborn screening.
So newborn screening is very
important to help patients
develop complications.
screening again irt with
secondary dna screen if
it's combined with the
newborn screen the result
for cystic fibrosis
confirmatory testing will
be dna sequencing okay
and sweat chloride testing
it's autonomic autosomal
recessive if both parents
are carriers 25 chance
of affected offspring
if one parent is affected
and one parent is a cf
carrier 50 chance if both
parents are affected with
cystic fibrosis 100 chance
and offspring is affected
which is rare um cystic
fibrosis carrier screening
again there is a 23 mutation
panel gene panel so any
of those genes could be
involved um if no personal
history or family history
the 23 panel of a single
person or female planning
on pregnancy if a known
cf carrier family history
then you want to screen
the family members as well
by the same lab and using
the panel appropriate for
the ethnic group okay so
cystic fibrosis treatment.
Better to have a team
care approach will help
improve the survival. We saw
pancreatic abnormalities,
so which means
nutrition, pancreatic
enzymes, fat soluble
proteins, mineral replacement,
high fat, high calorie diet,
mechanic therapy,
mechanically chest
physiotherapy and positive
expiratory pressure
ventilation and medications
include mucolytics and
bronchodilators and other
modulate cfti modulators
and antibiotics etc
transplantation if nothing
you know if these are
insufficient okay so if you
look at the right side you can
see how historically it
has been improving with the
advent of different treatment
And more and more newer
medications are emerging
and new studies coming that
will keep improving the
survival of patients with cystic
fibrosis if they take
adequate preventive care and,
you know, medical management
and surgical treatment.
And finally, alpha-1
antitrypsin deficiency,
AAT. So this is a major
genetic cause of chronic
obstructive pulmonary
disease in 1 to 3% of the
patients of COPD patients
have AAT deficiency.
AAT is a major protease
inhibitor in the lung.
If it is deficient, that
leads to unregulated
protease activity and early
emphysematous COPD. It's
expressed in the liver,
but acts in the lung.
Its inheritance is
autosomal recessive.
Remember the Serpene A1 gene.
Okay,
Serpene A1 gene mutations,
co-dominant with that.
Now,
AAT mutation carrier frequency
is 1 in 25 Caucasians,
and AAT incidence is 1 in
6,700 Caucasians affected.
Oops, my bad.
Feature, COPD, emphysematis,
hepatic cirrhosis,
the AZ diagnosis, hybrid
AZ diagnosis. Earlier
you can see COPD, later
you can see hepatitis,
paniculitis,
and then vasculitis,
glomerulonephritis. So
it's important to test
if cardinal features
are present, especially
if unexplained
early, you know,
presentations of this kind.
Diagnosis by antitrypsin
serum levels,
and then genotyping
of serpene A1
gene at the protease
inhibitor locus.
So if you see in
the electrophoresis
on the right, So, the
image on the right
says, which is the
most common type,
the medium migration or slow
migration or very
slow migration.
So, essentially what
you're doing is using gel
electrophoresis. If you see
the supplemental file, I would
have given an image. um
so so normal aat is m band
okay you will see m band in
it uh depending on the size
and protein folding
pattern it will migrate at
different rates in gel
electrophoresis remember last year
we discussed about that uh
the p p I d p I z z is the
most common disease phenotype
it's associated with
severe AAT deficiency from
AAT polymerization defect.
PIMZ is the most common carrier
phenotype and it's
occasionally mild
dysfunction. And if
it's a null phenotype,
null mutation is due to
complete deletion or due to
nonsense mutation with
undetected protein levels and
no migratory bands okay so
that's null so these are
the three different uh you
know phenotypes you can see
and functional assays are
also available copd monitor
and treat them as part
of management tobacco
abstinence of course
baseline pulmonary function
testing standard copd care
and then pooled human serum
AAT enzyme infusion so
there are enzyme infusion
options available if it's
indicated if fev1 fev1
is the force expiratory
volume fev1 I think and
that's if it's less than
65 percent or necrotizing
peniculitis and and then
lung raise it raises serum
AAT levels and it can slow
down the progression of the
pathology. Lung transplant
options if the FEV1 is
significantly low, less than
30% and age is less than 60.
There are also
bleeding therapies
and trials are
ongoing for this.
So overall summary is many
environmental exposures and
genetic syndromes are
associated with an increased
risk for CHDs and their
identification can aid in
prognosis anticipatory guidance
and reconnaissance risk
and many cardiovascular
conditions are associated with
genetic conditions um many
pulmonary conditions are
also associated we have seen
some representative examples
um but keep your um fall
for example purposes school
example process this is
what we'll focus on but for
boards you want to broaden
your understanding um so
um let's see what else can
we add um I've also given
uh case study based questions
and answers from these
links um and then these are
the reference materials um
this lecture is
definitely supplemental
lecture notes can help
you to some extent in
understanding a little
more about this some of
the slides I've given
slide numbers as well
and these are the textbooks
and that's I think
pretty much what I wanted
to say so thank you
for your attention and
try to see if I can add
anything so again how
do you study for this
mainly focus on the
different, go to this slide,
mainly focus on for which
syndrome or which you know
congenital condition you see
which cardiovascular defect.
And or when you see patients
with a known cardiovascular
effect, you should also
suspect any mild other
syndrome or mild presentation
of other conditions so
that they need to be, you
need to bring in consultancies
from other aspects as well
for a comprehensive care.
So you want to understand,
you want to remember the
genes specifically that are
involved and their major
clinical presentation as
I've highlighted in bold and
also other non-cardiac
presentation as well so that you
when you answer question
you can get a better picture
about what kind of a disease
condition the patient
may have or what is the
genetic cause likely genetic
cause or what diagnostic we
want so yeah sometimes you
what diagnostic test for
example in this case karyotyping
but mainly the the idea
is to learn about the
pathology um in these conditions
uh yeah I think that's
pretty much it if you have
any questions please feel
free to email me at vrajagop
at nyit.edu and thank you